Guide to the Kay Thode Papers
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
Kay Thode Papers
1962-2003
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections
5353
Thode, Kay
4 cubic feet 5 boxes and 1 oversize folder
Papers of Seattle social worker and welfare policy analyst who worked as director of the Seattle Urban League's Health and Welfare department
Social worker and welfare policy analyst Kay Thode worked as Director of the Seattle Urban League's Health and Welfare Department from 1968 to 1983. She subsequently worked as a planner for the King County Health Planning Council, a subarea council of the Puget Sound Health Systems Agency. Throughout her career she was tireless in advocating and lobbying for the rights of welfare recipients and the poor, and testified frequently before local, state, and federal government bodies. She was active in the Puget Sound Chapter of the National Association of Social Workers, serving as Newsletter Editor, President, and delegate to NASW's national assembly several times. At the organization's national level she was chair of the National Committee on Women's Issues and was a member of the National Social Policy and Action Cabinet. She was named Social Worker of the Year by the Puget Sound Council in 1972, and by the Washington State Chapter in 1979. She was also active in the Washington Association for Social Welfare, presenting a paper at its conference on The Worth of Work in, 1977, and serving as keynote speaker at its 1978 legislative conference. She was elected President of the organization in October 1979. She initiated the group Washington State Friends of Welfare Rights to support the activities of the Washington State and National Welfare Rights Organizations, and served on the boards of the Washington Coalition for a National Health Program, the Council of Planning Affiliates Legislative Comittee, Neighborhood Health Centers, the Fair Budget Action Campagn, the Welfare Rights Organizing Committee, and People for Fair Taxes. She also served on advisory committees for entities including King County Hospital, the Washington State Department of Social and Health Services, and Seattle City Light. Thode's husband Bob Thode appeared before the anti-Left Canwell Committee during the Red Scare of the 1950s--partly because of her activism.
The Kay Thode papers consist mainly of writings, speeches, testimony and other materials produced with, and on behalf of, the many organizations with which she worked, including the Seattle Urban League, Washington Association For Social Welfare, and Washington State Friends of Welfare Rights.
Organized into 2 accessions.
Accession No. 5353-003, Kay Thode papers, 1962-2003
Accession No. 5353-004, Kay Thode papers, 1974-1987
Some records are stored off site; advance notice required for use.
Open to all users.
See also Seattle Urban League records (Manuscript collection 0607)
Social workers; Thode, Kay$vArchives.; McLean, Elaine,$d1935-1975.; McLean, Elaine,$d1935-1975.; Seattle Urban League.; Washington Association for Social Welfare.; Washington State Welfare Rights Organization.; Seattle Urban League.; Seattle Urban League.$bHealth and Welfare Department.; Washington Association for Social Welfare.; Washington State Friends of Welfare Rights.; Washington State Welfare Rights Organization.; Washington (State)$xSocial policy$xResearch.; King County (Wash.)$xSocial policy$xResearch.; Seattle (Wash.)$xSocial policy$xResearch.; Women social workers$zWashington (State)$zSeattle$vArchives.; Community activists$zWashington (State)$zSeattle$vArchives.; Welfare rights movement$zWashington (State)$y20th century.; Human services$xResearch$zWashington (State); Poverty$xResearch$zWashington (State); Speeches, addresses, etc.; Poems.; Typescripts.; Writings.
Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Social and community history; Civic Activism; Medicine and Health; Washington (State)
- Kay Thode papers, 1962-2003; 5353-003; 3.64 cubic feet 4 boxes and 1 oversize folder
  The papers are arranged in ten series:
  Personal Papers, 1972-1996
  Council of Planning Affiliates, 1991, undated
  Fair Budget Action Campaign, 1987-1992, 1983-1985
  King County Health Planning Council (Puget Sound Health Systems Agency)
  National Association of Social Workers, Puget Sound Chapter, 1972-1978
  People for Fair Taxes in Washington, 1983, undated
  Seattle Urban League Health and Welfare Department, 1964-2003
  Toward an Open Society, 1964-1966
  Washington Association for Social Welfare, 1962-1982
  Washington State Friends of Welfare Rights, 1964-1975
  The collection consists largely of Kay Thode's writings, speeches, testimony and other materials produced with and on behalf of the organizations with which she worked; the largest proportion dates from her years with the Seattle Urban League. The record series "Fact Sheets" in the Seattle Urban League subgroup was created to include materials that Ms. Thode had labeled "Fact Sheets and Summaries" and includes her yearly "Washington State Welfare Facts" information sheets as well as background material gathered for its preparation, and other fact sheets on related topics. She continued her fact sheets after leaving the Seattle Urban League; the later fact sheets are in Personal Papers and other subgroups. Conference files and a limited amount of correspondence also are present, much of the latter in connection either with requesting information from government bodies and other organizations, or sending information to local and national legislators. The greater part of the remaining material (clippings, reports, ephemera and so forth) consists of supporting material for Ms. Thode's writings, testimony and lobbying efforts. The Speeches and Writings series in the Seattle Urban League subgroup includes Kay Thode's notes on Seattle Urban League staff in the late 1960s and early 1970s; these were written as commentary on the draft finding aid for the Seattle Urban League records, which are also housed in Special Collections Division (Box 3, Folder 29). A subject file in the Washington State Friends of Welfare Rights subgroup contains materials relating to Elaine McLean, a welfare activist (and former welfare recipient) who intitiated the Tacoma-based Welfare Rights Organizing Committee and includes McLean's poetry and her book manuscript, Carrots and Sticks and the Employable Welfare Poor. The personal papers subgroup contains a subject file titled "Uncompensated Care," covering Ms. Thode's work on that issue in conjunction with several different groups and organizations in the early 1980s. Other subgroups include professional organizations to which Thode belonged, such as the Puget Sound Chapter of the National Association of Social Workers, or groups with which she was active, such as Toward an Open Society, the Fair Budget Action Campaign, and Washington State Friends of Welfare Rights.
  Open to all users.
  Donated by Kay Thode in two installments in 2003.
  - Personal Papers, 1972-1996; Series 1
    - Incoming Letters, 1983, 1986-1989 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Writings
      - Letters to Editors, Seattle Times, 1987-1988, 1991-1992, undated (Box-folder 1/2)
      - "Welfare, A Critical Children's Issue", 1986-1987, undated (Box-folder 1/3)
      - Letter to Times re. abortion/welfare (Kay Thode's folder title), 1989 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Writings of Others
      - United Way Facts and Trends Report: A Working Paper, 1986 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Fact Sheets Regarding Welfare, 1986-1989 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Testimony
      - Department of Social and Health Services Forum on 1989-91 Budget Options, 1988 (Box-folder 1/7)
      - Testimony to House Ways and Means on Grants, 1989 (Box-folder 1/8)
      - Miscellaneous, 1989-1995, undated (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Conference and Convention Files
      - 'The Group Without a Name", 1972 (Box-folder 1/10-1/14)
        Includes Kay Thode's paper, general conference materials as well as papers delivered by other participants in a conference on women and leadership
      - Washington Coalition for a National Health Program, 1975 (Box-folder 1/15)
    - Ephemera: Welfare Reform Confidential, comic written by Alec Dubro and Mike Konopacki, drawings by Mike Konopacki, Jobs with Justice, pub., undated (Box-folder:oversize Miscellaneous Oversize Box 10)
    - Subject Files
      - Portfolio, 1975, undated (Box-folder 1/16)
        Includes speeches by Thode.
      - Washington State Department of Social and Health Services Depth Study Team (Letter from Mike Lowry), 1987 (Box-folder 1/17)
      - Washington (State) Human Services Task Force, 1992, 1993, undated (Box-folder 1/18)
    - Notes and Miscellany, 1986 (Box-folder 1/19)
    - Clippings, 1987, 1996 (Box-folder 1/20)
  - Council of Planning Affiliates, Series 2
    - Legislative Analysis Meeting, 1991, undated (Box-folder 1/21)
  - Fair Budget Action Campaign, 1987-1992; Series 3
    - Fact Sheets, 1987-1991 (Box-folder 1/22-1/25)
      - Legislative Handouts, 1990-1991,undated (Box-folder 1/26)
    - Testimony
      - Alliance for Children, Youth and Families, 1989-1991 (Box-folder 1/27)
    - Writings, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 1/28)
      Contains opinion pieces written for or published in the Seattle Times
    - Certificate of Recognition, 1992 (Box-folder 1/29)
    - Subject File: Washington Department of Social and Health Services Cost of Living Advisory Committee, 1990-1991, undated (Box-folder 1/30)
  - King County Health Planning Council (Puget Sound Health Systems Agency), 1983-1985; Series 4
    - Subject File: Uncompensated Care
      Thode's folder groupings and titles retained
      - Correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 1/31)
      - Testimony: Senate Ways and Means Hearing on Uncompensated Care, 1984 (Box-folder 1/32)
      - Reports
        - Legislative reports and testimony for WASW uncompensated care overview, 1983, undated (Box-folder 1/33)
        - "Uncompensated Care—An Overview of the Issues" (Puget Sound Health Systems Agency), 1983 (Box-folder 1/34)
        - "Uncompensated Care: A Major Ethical Issue" (King County Health Planning Council), 1984 (Box-folder 1/35)
      - Medical Assistance, 1985 (Box-folder 1/36)
      - Conference and Convention Files: "Innovations and Alliances", 1984 (Box-folder 1/37)
  - National Association of Social Workers, Puget Sound Chapter, 1972-1978; Series 5
    - Outgoing Letters, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 1/38)
    - Subject Files
      - Committee on Women's Issues, 1975-1978 (Box-folder 1/39)
      - Position Papers, 1972-1975
        - "Issues in Income Maintenance", 1973-1974 (Box-folder 1/40)
        - Position Paper on Public Assistance, 1972, 1975 (Box-folder 1/41)
  - People for Fair Taxes in Washington, Series 6
    - Subject File; Washington State Budget, 1983-1985 biennium, 1983, undated (Box-folder 1/42-1/44)
  - Seattle Urban League Health and Welfare Department, 1964-2003; Series 7
    - Organizational Features, 1977, 1981-1983, undated (Box-folder 2/1)
    - Incoming Letters, 1969, 1974, 1980-1983 (Box-folder 2/2)
    - Outgoing Letters, 1968-1983 (Box-folder 2/3-2/12)
    - General Correspondence, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 2/13)
    - Intra-Organizational Correspondence, Seattle Urban League, 1970-1975 (Box-folder 2/14)
    - Interoffice Correspondence, National Urban League, 1970-1973 (Box-folder 2/15)
    - Reports: Seattle Urban League
      - Seattle Urban League Reports, 1968, 1971, 1981 (Box-folder 2/16)
        Include contributions by Thode.
      - Health and Welfare Committee Reports, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 2/17)
        "King County Hospital—A New Look?" and "Minority Representation in Seattle Area Hospitals"
      - "Seattle Urban League Tax Position" (prepared by Kay Thode), 1977 (Box-folder 2/18)
      - "Early Periodic Screening, Diagnosis and Treatment in Washington", 1974 (Box-folder 2/19)
      - "Child Abuse and Neglect Project Final Report", 1982 (Box-folder 2/20)
      - Health and Welfare Department Reports—Program, Annual and Legislative, 1977, 1979-1980, 1983 (Box-folder 2/21)
    - Reports: Other Organizations
      - "Survey of Health Facilities of Manpower Resources in Inner-City Areas" (National Urban League)(Appendices E-G only—surveys and maps), undated (Box-folder 2/22)
      - "Wingspread Report—Health Issues and Minority Communities" (National Urban League), 1973 (Box-folder 2/23)
      - "Sources—Health Problems of the Poor" (Blue Cross), undated (Box-folder 2/24)
      - "Public Welfare: Poverty—Prevention or Perpetuation?" (Washington State Department of Public Assistance), 1964 (Box-folder 2/25)
      - "An Analysis of Unemployment and the Food Problem in the Central Puget Sound Region" (Puget Sound Governmental Conference), 1971 (Box-folder 2/26)
      - "Report on the Status of Nutrition and Hunger in King County" (William A. Little), 1973 (Box-folder 2/27)
    - Conference and Convention Files, 1976, 1982
      - Freedom From Want: Towards More Equality (Seattle Urban League), 1976 (Box-folder 2/28)
        Conference attendees' packet
      - Freedom From Want, 1976 (Box-folder 2/29)
        Manuscript of conference proceedings
      - Freedom From Want, 1976 (Box-folder 2/30)
        Published conference proceedings
      - U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare—Women and Welfare, 1976 (Box-folder 2/31)
      - [Washington] Governor's Conference on Health Care Financing, 1982 (Box-folder 2/32)
    - Testimony
      - President's Commission on Income Maintenance, 1969 (Box-folder 2/33)
      - Appropriations Committee, 1970 (Box-folder 2/34)
      - Senate Appropriations Committee, 1971 (Box-folder 2/35)
      - House Ways and Means, 1971 (Box-folder 2/36)
      - Social and Health Services Subcommittee, 1973 (Box-folder 2/37)
      - Ways and Means Committee, 1974 (Box-folder 2/38)
      - United States House of Representatives Ways and Means, 1974 (Box-folder 2/39)
        Testimony of Ronald Brown, National Urban League Washington Bureau, prepared by Kay Thode
      - Seattle City Council, 1974 (Box-folder 2/40)
      - Joint Ways and Means, 1975 (Box-folder 2/41)
      - Subcommittee on Health, United States Ways and Means, 1976 (Box-folder 2/42)
      - Transportation and Utilities Committee, 1976 (Box-folder 2/43)
      - Welfare Reform Committee, United States House of Representatives, 1977 (Box-folder 2/44)
      - Regional Hearing on Welfare Reform, 1977 (Box-folder 2/45)
      - Bishop's Urban Coalition Hearings, 1978 (Box-folder 2/46)
      - Washington State Legislature, House Labor Committee, 1978 (Box-folder 2/47)
      - United Presbyterian Task Force, 1979 (Box-folder 2/48)
      - Human Resources Subcommittee, House Appropriations Committee, 1979 (Box-folder 2/49)
      - Senate Ways and Means Committee, 1979 (Box-folder 2/50)
      - Planning and Community Affairs Agency Hearing on Poverty, 1980 (Box-folder 2/51)
      - National Democratic Party Platform Committee, 1980 (Box-folder 2/52)
      - House Appropriations Committee, 1980 (Box-folder 2/53)
      - Department of Social and Health Services Rule Changes, 1980 (Box-folder 2/54)
      - House Human Services Committee, 1981 (Box-folder 2/55)
        Testimony of Dorothy DeCoster, Seattle Urban League
      - House Ways and Means, 1981 (Box-folder 2/56)
        Testimony of Spruiell White, Director, Seattle Urban League; prepared by Kay Thode
      - Area Plan for Aging, 1981 (Box-folder 2/57)
        Testimony of Orie Green, Seattle Urban League Board Chairman
      - Department of Social and Health Services, 1981 (Box-folder 2/58)
      - Human Services Committee, 1981 (Box-folder 2/59)
      - Department of Social and Health Services Rule Changes, 1981 (Box-folder 2/60)
      - Department of Social and Health Services Perspective on Implementation of Federal Budget Reductions and Block Grants, 1981 (Box-folder 2/61)
      - Committee on Ways and Means, United States House of Representatives, Regional Field Hearing, 1982 (Box-folder 2/62)
      - Governor's Tax Advisory Council, 1982 (Box-folder 2/63)
      - Senate Ways and Means, 1982 (Box-folder 2/64)
      - Deborah Bowler, Hunger Action Center, 1977 (Box-folder 2/65)
    - Speeches and Writings
      - "H.R. 1—Hope for the Financial Future of the Elderly?", 1972 (Box-folder:oversize Miscellaneous Oversize Box 10)
        In Office of the Governor Human Affairs Council News
      - Letters to editor, letters to broadcasters, 1971, 1979, 1981-1982, undated (Box-folder 3/1)
      - "Impact of the 'Political Process' on Application of Social Justice Principles to Income Maintenance Legislation", 1972 (Box-folder 3/2)
      - "Alternatives to Hunger", 1972 (Box-folder 3/3)
      - "Public Assistance Grants and the Poverty Level: A Comparison", 1974 (Box-folder 3/4)
      - "Public Assistance and the Law", 1975 (Box-folder 3/5)
      - "Welfare Reform", 1975 (Box-folder 3/6)
      - "The Poverty Index", 1975 (Box-folder 3/7)
      - "Public Assistance in Washington State—Issues for the 1976 Legislature", 1975 (Box-folder 3/8)
      - Position Statement for Department of Social and Health Services Advisory Committee, 1976 (Box-folder 3/9)
      - "Work, Women and Welfare", 1977 (Box-folder 3/10)
        Presented at The Worth of Work, Washington Association for Social Welfare conference
      - "Welfare Grant Cuts—Illegal, Immoral and Uneconomical", 1978 (Box-folder 3/11)
      - "The Worst of Our Crimes", 1978 (Box-folder 3/12)
        Sermon delivered at University Unitarian Church
      - "Social Welfare Dilemmas Facing Washington Residents", 1978 (Box-folder 3/13)
        Keynote speech, Washington Association for Social Welfare Legislative Workshop
      - "A Policy for Families and Children", 1978 (Box-folder 3/14)
      - "Poverty—The Critical Women's Issue", 1979 (Box-folder 3/15)
      - "Hungry People in the 'Most Livable' City—Why?", 1979 (Box-folder 3/16)
      - Social Work Graduating Address, Eastern Washington University, 1979 (Box-folder 3/17)
      - Welfare Coalition press statement, 1980 (Box-folder 3/18)
      - "Health Issues Report", 1980 (Box-folder 3/19)
      - "The Poor and the 1981 Legislature" (Box-folder 3/20)
      - From Mayor's Conference, 1981 (Box-folder 3/21)
      - "Review and Analysis: November 1981 Special Legislative Session" (draft) (Box-folder 3/22)
        Prepared for Seattle Urban League report; a finished copy is in the Seattle Urban League Reports folder
      - "The 1981 Legislature and the Poor in Washington State" (Box-folder 3/23)
        Article in Seattle's Capitol Report
      - "Alert!", 1981 (Box-folder 3/24)
      - "Women and Welfare", 1981 (Box-folder 3/25)
        Panel presentation for the 11th Far West Regional Conference on Women and the Law
      - Statement to Congressman Pritchard, 1982 (Box-folder 3/26)
      - Keynote address to South Snohomish County Association of Churches, 1982 (Box-folder 3/27)
      - Notes of speech made to Church Women United, 1982 (Box-folder 3/28)
      - Kay Thode's Recollections of the Seattle Urban League, Its Staff and Programs, 2003 (Box-folder 3/29)
    - Speeches and Writings of Others
      - "A Comparative Study of the Perception of the Quality of Health Care at King County Hospital and Other Seattle Hospitals" (Judith Ann Tapley), 1968 (Box-folder 3/30)
      - "A Survey of Medical Cost Containment Measures" (Mij Woodward), 1980 (Box-folder 3/31)
    - Fact Sheets, 1969-1983 (Box-folder 3/32-3/53)
      Includes annual versions of "Washington State Welfare Facts," often foldered with background material and preparation notes as well as fact sheets on related subjects, and packets of material prepared for legislators.
    - Subject Files
      - Cost of Raising a Child, 1979-1982, undated (Box-folder 3/54)
      - Day Care, 1966-1967, undated (Box-folder 3/55)
      - Department of Social and Health Services Cuts 1981-83 Biennium, 1982, undated (Box-folder 3/56-3/58)
      - Elizabethan Poor Law—relative responsibility—HB1161, 1975, undated (Box-folder 3/59)
      - Impact of 1980-81 Cuts on Individual Clients—Calls re. CEAP etc., 1981 (Box-folder 3/60)
      - Proposal on Hypertension (Seattle Urban League), 1978 (Box-folder 3/61)
      - Seattle Urban League Participation in Health Director Search, Seattle-King County, 1971 (Box-folder 3/62)
      - Teach-In On Welfare, 1969 (Box-folder 3/63)
    - Legislation: Washington (State) H.B. 245, 1981 (Box-folder 3/64)
    - Newsletters: Seattle Urban League and National Urban League, 1972, 1974 (Box-folder 3/65)
    - Photographs, ca. 1975, undated (Box-folder 3/66)
      One 3.5" x 5" color snapshot (very faded) of Gerret Kowenhoven, circa 1975; one 5" x 7" black-and-white photograph of Edwin T. Pratt
    - Questionnaire, 1968 (Box-folder 3/67)
    - Certificate: University of Washington School of Social Work, 1979 (Box-folder 3/68)
    - Handbook: Practicum Instruction, University of Washington School of Social Work, 1980, undated (Box-folder 3/69-3/70)
    - Clippings, 1971, 1976, 1980, 1983 (Box-folder 3/71)
    - Notes, 1967, undated (Box-folder 3/72)
  - Toward an Open Society, 1964-1966; Series 8
    Toward an Open Society was a group whose goal was to promote social harmony through integration of schools, achieved by promoting fair housing policies; Thode participated in the organization when her children were attending Hamilton Middle School.
    - Reports, Handbooks, Brochures and other materials, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 4/1)
    - Reprint: Article on Eichler Homes, 1964 (Box-folder:oversize Miscellaneous Oversize Box 10)
    - Ephemera: Flyer In Support of Washington (State) S.J.R. 20, undated (Box-folder:oversize Miscellaneous Oversize Box 10)
  - Washington Association for Social Welfare, 1962-1982; Series 9
    - Bylaws, 1962 (Box-folder 4/2)
    - Bluebook, undated (Box-folder 4/3)
    - General Correspondence, 1979-1980, 1982 (Box-folder 4/4)
    - Minutes: Board Meetings, 1982-1984 (Box-folder 4/5)
    - Conference and Convention Files: "A Child's World, Today and Tomorrow", 1972, 1977, 1982 (Box-folder 4/6)
    - Fact Sheets, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 4/7)
    - Testimony, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 4/8)
      Testimony for hearing on the economic assistance policy options, 1981; testimony on H.B. 1194 and H.J.R. 26 to House Revenue Committee, 1982
  - Washington State Friends of Welfare Rights, 1964-1975; Series 10
    - Organizational Features
      - Washington State Welfare Rights Organization, undated (Box-folder 4/9)
      - National Welfare Rights Organization, undated (Box-folder 4/10)
    - General Correspondence (Box-folder 4/11-4/12)
      Major correspondent: National Welfare Rights Organization. Also includes correspondence of Washington State Welfare Rights Organization.
    - Newsletters, 1971-1972, 1974 (Box-folder 4/13)
      Friends of Welfare Rights and other organizations
    - Conference and Convention Files, 1970, undated (Box-folder 4/14)
      National Welfare Rights Organization
    - Speeches and Writings (Box-folder 4/15)
    - Membership Lists, undated (Box-folder 4/16)
    - Subject File: Elaine McLean
      Material by and relating to Elaine McLean of the Tacoma-based Welfare Rights Action Council
      - Memorial Program and Obituary, 1971-1972, 1975, undated (Box-folder 4/17)
        Also includes other welfare-related material.
      - Speeches and Writings, 1971-1973, undated
        - Who Is the Loser in the WIN Program?: Washington State Service Delivery(typescript), undated (Box-folder 4/18)
        - Carrots and Sticks and the Employable Welfare Poor(typescript) (Box-folder 4/19)
        - Poems (typescripts), undated (Box-folder 4/20)
        - Miscellaneous Short Pieces, 1972-1973, undated (Box-folder 4/21)
        - "Freedom" (photocopy of handwritten poem, undated (Box-folder:oversize Miscellaneous Oversize Box 10)
      - Newsletters